<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: xampp | henning glatter-götz]]></title>
  <link href="http://glatter-gotz.com/blog/categories/xampp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glatter-gotz.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-22T12:50:54+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://glatter-gotz.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Henning Glatter-Götz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Connecting to Microsoft SQL Server from PHP on OSX and XAMPP]]></title>
    <link href="http://glatter-gotz.com/blog/2011/06/06/connecting-to-microsoft-sql-server-from-php-on-osx-and-xampp/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://glatter-gotz.com/blog/2011/06/06/connecting-to-microsoft-sql-server-from-php-on-osx-and-xampp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><h4>UPDATE (March 23rd 2012):</h4>

<p>I recently found a <a href="http://php-osx.liip.ch/">PHP binary </a>that has a one-line installer. It is actively maintained by Liip AG. I now use that in combination with <a href="http://mxcl.github.com/homebrew/">HomeBrew</a> for all the rest. The Liip package is compiled with pdo_dblib which makes the problem described in this post a non-issue.</p></blockquote>

<p>I recently found myself in the position of having to connect to a remote Microsoft SQL Server from my OSX system using PHP. The production environment runs Ubuntu LINUX, where connecting via mssql_connect() was no problem, but I develop on OSX and I could not get this to work initially.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>mssql_connect() simply returns boolean FALSE on failure and PHP tells you little more than</p>

<p><code>bash
Warning: mssql_connect(): Unable to connect to server: YOURSERVERNAME
</code></p>

<p>It took quite a few hours to finally figure out that I could turn on some additional logging on the driver level. I use XAMPP and its PHP distribution uses FreeTDS for mssql access.
There is a configuration file for this driver located at</p>

<p><code>bash
/Applications/XAMPP/xamppfiles/etc/freetds.conf
</code></p>

<p>that lets you turn on debug logging to a file.</p>

<p>Uncomment the following lines</p>

<p><code>bash
;       dump file = /tmp/freetds.log
;       debug flags = 0xffff
</code></p>

<p>And then run your connection attempt again. Take a look at the log for details on the failure.</p>

<p>In the end I added a new entry for an MS SQL server at the end of the freetds.conf file and used its name in the call to mssql_connect().</p>

<p>``` bash
[MyServerXYZ]</p>

<pre><code>    host = the_host_name
    instance = the_instance_name
    port = 1433
    tds version = 9.0
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>In my case I had to deal with an instance name that would normally be appended to the host name in a connection string, but for this driver configuration you have to use a variable called <em>instance</em>.</p>

<p>In PHP I then use this code during development</p>

<p><code>bash
$conn = mssql_connect('MyServerXYZ', $username, $password);
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
