<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ember | henning glatter-götz]]></title>
  <link href="http://glatter-gotz.com/blog/categories/ember/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://glatter-gotz.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-04T23:09:03+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://glatter-gotz.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Henning Glatter-Götz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ember.js Resources]]></title>
    <link href="http://glatter-gotz.com/blog/2015/01/05/ember-dot-js-resources/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-05T04:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://glatter-gotz.com/blog/2015/01/05/ember-dot-js-resources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Please note that this was published in January of 2015. So keep in mind that the
shelf-life is limited</p></blockquote>

<p>The following is a helpful list of where to find current information on Ember.js:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>The best place to start is the Ember website itself <a href="http://emberjs.com">emberjs.com</a>.
The docs live there and on the blog you can find current news on the project.</li>
<li><a href="http://emberweekly.com/">Ember Weekly</a> is a newsletter all about ember. It is an
outstanding aggregation of what is happening in the Ember ecosystem.</li>
</ul>


<p>Two recent podcasts with great info about the upcoming Ember 2.0 release:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://frontsidethepodcast.simplecast.fm/16"><strong>Frontside the Podcast: Ember 2.0 and the Indie Web with Yehuda Katz and Tom Dale</strong></a><br/>
This is a fairly new podcast that I came across recently. This episode from December
23rd 2014 features Tom Dale and Yehuda Katz and they talk about current work on
Ember.js.</p>

<p>Highlights:</p>

<ul>
<li>HTMLBars - Complete replacement of the render engine</li>
<li>FastBoot - server side rendering</li>
<li>Important aspects of running a successful OSS project</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://thechangelog.com/131/"><strong>The Changelog: The road to Ember 2.0 with Tom Dale and Yehuda Katz</strong></a><br/>
Similar info to the previous one</p></li>
<li><p>The Ember.js <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/EmberNYC">Meetup in NYC</a> is probably one of the most professional I have found.
The meetings are all recorded and core team members speak there on a regular basis.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
